Vernon Greene Papers
Vernon Greene Papers
1922-1966
Greene, Vernon Van Atta.
42.5 linear ft.
Proofs and tear sheets from a wide variety of comic strips, original drawings, sketches, correspondence, biographical material, published material and taped interviews.
2655686
Biographical History
Vernon Van Atta Greene (1908-1965) was an American cartoonist and illustrator, most noted for his work as George McManus' successor on the comic strip Bringing Up Father.
Greene was born in Battle Ground, Washington in 1908, one of seven children. Greene spent much of his early career doing sports and editorial cartoons for various newspapers, including the Portland (Ore.) Telegram (1927-1929), the Toledo Blade (1930-1932) and the New York Mirror (1934-1937). During this time, Greene was also an active freelance illustrator, creating advertising cartoons and illustrations for books and magazines, working on Street and Smith publications like the Shadow and the Masked Lady, and ghosting for many years on the daily version of Cliff Sterrett's comic strip Polly and Her Pals.
During WWII, Greene found himself with the medical division of the Air Corps as a photographer at Kearns Air Base in Utah. After the war was active in traveling USO tours with other cartoonists. He attended Toledo University in the 1930s and following World War II, Columbia University.
In 1954, Greene took over the long-running classic comic strip Bringing Up Father after the death of the strip's creator George McManus. He carried on with the strip, maintaining it very much in McManus' signature style, until his own death in 1965.
In addition to his prolific artistic output, Greene also served as host of the WRVR syndicated radio show The Cartoonist's Art, and was an active member of the National Cartoonists Society, serving two years as Vice President. In 1964, Greene was awarded the NCS Silver T-Square award for his service to his profession.
Vernon Greene died in 1965.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The vast majority of the Vernon Greene Papers consists of proofs and tear sheets from a large diversity of daily and Sunday comic strips—hundreds of different titles and artists, ranging primarily through the 1930s and 1940s. The collection also contains a substantial amount of material related specifically to Vernon Greene, including original artworks and sketches done by Greene, published samples of his cartoon and illustration work, correspondence, biographical material and a tape recorded interview.
Correspondence (1929-1966) contains seven boxes of incoming correspondence addressed to Greene and later to his widow. Much of the correspondence is from other cartoonists and there is also fan mail. The holiday cards often feature cartoon designs and detailed correspondence from their senders. Later correspondence deals with Greene's hospitalization towards the end of his life in 1965. Among the letters of encouragement Greene received is a letter from Charles Schulz.
Personal files contains material related to Greene's family, property in New Jersey and student work from his time at Columbia University.
Photos consists primarily of news photos on a variety topics. Present are many news service photographs, almost exclusively from the International News Service, a unit of King Features. These photographs have been sorted and arranged by broad topics including Animals, Accidents/Disasters/Crime, Military, International Affairs, Sports, Labor Strikes (including the General Electric strike and Hollywood studio strikes) and New York City. The majority are contain the tag line, "Watch Your Credit". Attached to photos are typed summaries of what is depicted and datelines. War photos include combat manuevers in specific countries, individual soldiers, and items depicting social effects of the war. Imagery includes prisoners of war, civilian life, aftermath of battles and troops. Of particular interest is a photograph of Charles De Gaulle. A large set of images about the U.S. homefront is also contained in this series, particular images related to brides and returning veterans facing a housing shortage as well as a handful of images about rationing. Also of interest are photos of famous political figures and celebrities, including Albert Einstein, Humphrey Bogart, Dwight Eisenhower, Harry Truman, and images of a young Lucille Ball.
Another large area are photos of crime, accidents and disasters. These include crime scene photos (often graphic), women accused of committing violent crime, crimes against children, transportation accidents and fires. Sports contains images, particularly baseball, including the New York Yankees, as well as college basketball including Syracuse University and horse racing.
The Professional files series contains material related to Greene's involvement in the National Cartoonists Society and the Newspaper Comics Council. The NCS subseries contains correspondence, publications as well as audio recordings. The organization's newsletters have been cataloged and transferred to Rare Books. The Newspaper Comics Council subseries includes meeting minutes and membership lists. Worth noting is material on the topic of H.R. 7927 regarding postal rate increases.
Published and printed material contains biographical material about other cartoonists, various clippings related to Greene and promotional material. Of interest are Jim Ivey's "Report on European Political Cartooning" and advertising sales information for Puck, the Comic Weekly.
Reference files contains material amassed by Greene on a variety of topics. Included is typically printed and published material, clippings, photographs and occasionally correspondence. Of interest may be a Little Scouts Comic book in the Scouts file. Much Reference File material stamped with name Donald Beck
Works by Greene covers Greene's professional career as a cartoonist and illustrator. Items include material related to Greene's work on comic strips and commercial advertising artwork. The bulk of the comic strip related works pertains to Bringing Up Father. A large portion of proofs for Bringing Up Father were arranged by Greene by subject.
Works by others comprises the bulk of this collection. This series contains primarily proofs of comic strips from the 1930s and 1940s as well as tearsheets. Many of the proofs are full color.
Arrangement of the Collection
Materials from the same comic strip are at times not housed together because of their varying specific dimensions. Tape recordings appearing in several series have been numbered.
Related Material
has collections of more than 150 cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Additional The Heart of Juliet Jones cartoons are located in the
Stan Drake Papers
.
Additional material by Roy Crane is located in the
Roy Crane Papers
.
Additional "Cap" Stubbs and Tippie, Tippie and Brick Bradford proofs are located in the
C. D. Russell Cartoons
.
Additional Moon Mullins cartoons are located in the
Frank Willard Cartoons
.
Separated Material
Al Posen material has been transferred to the
Alvah Posen Collection
. Newsletters of the Newspaper Comics Council have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging; please refer to to locate these items.
Other Finding Aids
A set of index cards listing correspondents and dates is located in Box 6. However, the inclusiveness of this cross reference has not been verified.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Greene, Vernon Van Atta.; King Features Syndicate.; National Cartoonists Society.; Newspaper Comics Council.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; Crime scenes -- Pictorial works.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Pictorial works.; Audiocassettes.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Cartoons (humorous images); Photographs.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Barbara Greene.
Original artwork for Cherry and the Colonel, gift of Karl H. Schadow, 2013.
One 1960 correspondence item, gift of Alan Dedrick, 2015.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [Chronological], 1926 Apr; 1929 May-Nov,; 1930-1935; 9 folders (Box 1)
  - [Chronological], 1936 Jan-1944 Jan; 1945 Mar-1952 Dec; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - [Chronological], 1953 Jan-1957 Nov; 1958 Jan-1959 Dec; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - [Chronological], 1960-1963; 5 folders (Box 4)
    Signed greeting card dated 1960, gift of Alan Dedrick.
  - [Chronological], 1964; 1965 Jan-1966 May; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Christmas greetings, 1936-1966; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Christmas greetings, A-W, undated; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Christmas greetings, unidentified, undated (Box 7)
  - A-G, undated (Box 6)
  - Greene family, undated (Box 6)
  - H-Y, unidentified, undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Index by correspondent, Undated; set of index cards for correspondents with dates of correspondence (Box 6)
- Personal files
  - Army discharge certificate, Sep 28 1945 (Box 20)
  - Awards and certificates, 1954-1959 (Box 20)
  - Biographical material, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 20)
  - Calendars, 1937-1941; 1949,; 1954,; 1958-1959,; 1961-1962 (Oversize 5)
  - Columbia University
    - Class papers and notes, circa 1948-1955; 4 folders (Box 20)
    - Class papers, philosophy and social science, circa 1948-1955 (Box 20)
    - Notebook, 1954 (Box 21)
    - Records, 1948-1949; undated (Box 21)
  - Greene, Jill, circa 1950s; coloring book (Box 21)
  - Greene, Vernon's mother, undated (Box 21)
  - Personal notes as a cartoonist, undated (Box 21)
  - Personal notes (notebook pages), undated (Box 21)
  - Photos, Columbia University, undated (Box 21)
  - Photos, family, undated (Box 21)
  - Property records, 1952-1958; 1960; information about house, mortgage and tax payments; 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Sketches by Greene's children, 1950s-1960s (Box 22)
  - Sketchbooks, undated (Box 22)
  - Station Hospital Book (Kearns, Utah), circa 1940s (Box 22)
  - Toledo University Blockhouse Book, 1932 (Box 22)
  - Toledo University Records, 1932 (Box 22)
  - Valentine's Day card, undated (Box 21)
- Photos
  - News service photos
    - Airplanes (Box 36)
    - American Indians (Box 36)
    - Animals (Box 36)
    - Cartoonists and comic book artists (Box 36)
    - Celebrities and fashion, 2 folders (Box 36)
    - Celebrities and fashion, Lucille Ball (Box 36)
    - Chiang Kai-Shek (Box 36)
    - China (Box 36)
    - Crime, accidents and disasters, 4 folders (Box 36)
    - Israel and Palestine, 2 folders (Box 37)
    - Johnson, Lyndon B. (Box 37)
    - Korea (Box 37)
    - Labor strikes, 3 folders (Box 37)
    - New York City and New York State, 2 folders (Box 38)
    - Politics, political and business leaders, 3 folders (Box 38)
    - Religion (Box 38)
    - Sports, 3 folders (Box 39)
    - Truman, Harry S. (Box 39)
    - United Nations Monetary & Financial Conference (Box 39)
    - World War II, Britain (Box 39)
    - World War II, France (Box 39)
    - World War II, general, 3 folders (Box 39)
    - World War II, Germany, 2 folders (Box 40)
    - World War II, homefront, 2 folders (Box 40)
    - World War II, Italy (Box 40)
    - World War II, Japan (Box 40)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 40)
    - Unidentified (Box 40)
  - Subject files
    - 110th Street Community Center, 1948; undated; also includes some printed material (Box 33)
    - Arrow Service Club, circa 1940s (Box 33)
    - Circus show, circa 1940s; photos of a circus show on television. Photos of a television show; 3 folders (Box 33)
    - Dot and Gus, 1952 (Box 33)
    - Europe, contact sheets, 1956 (Box 33)
    - Female figure, undated; 3 folders (Box 34)
    - Greene, Vernon, undated; 2 folders (Box 34)
    - King Features Syndicate dinners and outings, undated (Box 34)
    - Professional stars and models, 1932-1934; undated (Box 34)
    - TAU, undated; mostly children in a parade (Box 34)
    - United States Carswell Air Force Base, Fort Worth, Texas, 1951 (Box 34)
    - USO show, circa 1953-1954 (Box 35)
    - USO show, Anchorage, Alaska, 1954 (Box 35)
    - USO camp show, Caribbean, 1964 (Box 35)
    - USO show, Japan, 1953 (Box 35)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; 7 folders (Box 35)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; large print of Greene at drawing board with seven men, possibly other cartoonists, note on back; 1 item (Oversize 29)
  - Negatives
    - Cartoonist European Shots for Stars & Stripes, 1953 (Box 44)
    - Family Christmas cards, 1957; undated (Box 44)
    - Greene and family, undated (Box 44)
      Includes one photo.
    - Japan, 1953; 1955; includes contact sheets; 2 folders (Box 44)
    - Japan, Cape Cod, Gracie, 1957 (Box 44)
    - Official Navy images, 1964 Mar; undated (Box 44)
    - Proofs of artwork, undated (Box 44)
    - Unidentified and West Coast, 1963 Jan (Box 44)
    - Unidentified, undated; 3 folders (Box 44)
- Professional files
  - National Cartoonists Society
    - Activities
      - American Newspaper Publishers Association Annual Meeting, 1963 (Box 8)
      - Annual Billy DeBeck Award dinner, 1952; 1954,; 1958 (Box 8)
      - Annual Luncheon for the benefit of the Milt Gross Fund, 1963 (Box 8)
      - Annual Reuben Awards Dinner correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box 8)
      - Annual Reuben Awards Dinner published material, 1955; 1959-1965 (Box 8)
      - Board of Governors, 1958; 1963 (Box 8)
      - Boy Scouts of America, undated (Box 8)
      - Camp Shows Committee, 1956; 1964 (Box 8)
      - Cartoonists' Night, 1963 (Box 8)
      - Constitution Committee, circa 1960s (Box 8)
      - Dinner Committee, 1964 (Box 9)
      - Dinner, Overseas Press Club, 1964 (Box 9)
      - Elections, undated (Box 9)
      - Eulogy for Al Posen, undated; 1960 (Box 9)
      - Goldberg, Rube, 1963; 80th birthday luncheon (Box 9)
      - Hands and Faces promotional material, undated (Box 9)
      - International cartoonists convention tour, 1961 (Box 9)
      - International golf tournament, 1959-1962 (Box 9)
      - Itineraries, 1949; undated (Box 9)
      - Itinerary for cartoonists unit, undated (Box 9)
      - Meeting minutes, undated (Box 9)
      - New directions dinner, 1963 (Box 9)
      - Nominating committee, 1960 (Box 9)
      - Nominating committee, Greene's nomination, 1960 (Box 9)
      - Notes by Greene, undated (Box 9)
      - President's report, 1959; 1961-1962 (Box 9)
      - Projects, undated (Box 9)
      - Reuben Awards notices, 1958-1965 (Box 9)
      - Roth, Ben, undated (Box 9)
      - Rosters, 1949; 1952-1954,; 1960; 1963 (Box 9)
      - Shows, 1961-1962; 1964 (Box 9)
      - Statement on H.R. 7927, 1962 Jul (Box 9)
      - U.S. Savings Bonds, 1961-1962 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence
      - Correspondence, 1951 Oct; 1952 Feb-Mar,; Sep 13 1952,; 1953-1959; 4 folders (Box 8)
      - Correspondence with Al Posen, 1959 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, 1960-1962; 1963 Feb-Jul,; Jun 3 1964; 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, undated (Box 8)
    - Publications
      - Annual report, 1961 (Box 9)
      - Comic Art, undated (Box 9)
      - Editor and Publisher, 1963; undated; clippings from (Box 9)
      - Newsletters, Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
      - New York Cartoon News, Oct 1 1953 (Box 9)
      - Placement service bulletins, 1958-1964 (Box 9)
      - This is a Must Magazine, circa 1960s (Box 9)
    - Recordings, tapes have multiple handwritten titles and notations, therefore the titles listed below may not completely reflect what is on each recording.; 35 items (Oversize 25)
      1: Abner, Dean, 1963
      2: Lewis, Boyd- NEA, undated
      3: Caniff, Milt, World's Fair, 1964
      4: Capp, Al, undated
      5: Career night / Al Posen and Rube Goldberg, 1959 / censorship / Russian history / Cartoon show Paramus
      6: Clark AFB- Al Posen, Vern Greene and others, undated
      7: Crawford, William: Banshees, undated
      8: Editor's Night, 1959
      9: Editorial, April 22, 1963
      10: Erwin, Rae; Fowler, Virginia; Troup, Millie and others, undated
      11: Feiffer, Jules; Shepherd, Gene and others, 1959
      12: Gag Cartoonists Discuss Their Ways of Working, undated
      13: Goldberg, Rube, tribute to Ed Valtman, 1962 / NCS Banquet / HR 2729
      14: Greene, Vernon and Harmon, Fred, undated
      15: Hershfield, Al interviewed by Patricia Marx, 1963
      16: Hodgkins, A., undated
      17: NCS Meetings, 1958
      18: NCS Meeting, undated
      19: Nomination of Officers, Hotel Astor, 1963
      20: Nomination speeches, Jan 1959
      21: Nomination speeches, 1960
      22: Nomination speeches, 1963 / Roy Crane April 2, 1964
      23: Shoptalk, undated
      24: Overseas Press Club, Oct 23, 1963 / Jimmy Hatlo / Shop Talk- Sol Stein
      25: Pulitzer Prize cartoonist, undated
      26: The Political Cartoon: Walt Kelly; Dan Dowling; Jules Feiffer, 1963 / Herblock, talk by the cartoonist
      27: Russian cartoonists / Sound of humor Frankel, undated
      28: Shop Talk / J. Robinson, undated
      29: NCS meeting / Lee Cass, undated
      30: Sutherland, Joan, undated
      31: What's So Funny, Mort Sahl, Jules Feiffer and others / Krazy Kat- recreation of comic strip / Ross Lews by Bill Crawford / Chester Gould, undated
      32: Herblock and Crawford / Harry Hershfield / Al Capp, undated
      33: Meeting, 1958 / NCS dinner
      34: Nomination speeches, 1963
      35: Unidentified, 1963
      55. Unidentified, undated.
  - Newspaper Comics Council
    - Addresses, 1959 (Box 10)
    - Agendas, 1958-1962 (Box 10)
    - Annual comics contest, 1958-1959 (Box 10)
    - Bulletins, 1958-1964 (Box 10)
    - Cartoonists Committee, undated (Box 10)
    - Comics pages for American Newspaper Publishers' Association, 1960s (Box 10)
    - Comics page- "Duke Handy" Philip Morris Cigarette Ad, 1957
    - Correspondence, 1956-1964 (Box 10)
    - "Duke Handy"- Phillip Morris cigarette advertising, 1957; color (Oversize 23)
    - Editorials, 1958; 1962; reprints (Box 10)
    - Exchange proposal- U.S. & U.S.S.R., 1958 (Box 10)
    - Gould, Chester (published material about Dick Tracy's creator), 1958 (Box 10)
    - Humor in cartoon art, 1958; published material written by Al Capp and Milt Caniff (Box 10)
    - House Cleaning with the Gold Dust Twins, 1932; color advertising proof for Gold Dust Scouring Powder (Oversize 23)
    - International newspaper comics contest reports, 1957-1958; 1960 (Box 10)
    - List of publications, undated (Box 10)
    - Meeting minutes, 1958-1963 (Box 10)
    - Membership lists, 1956-1962; also includes one issue of Madison Avenue magazine, Sep 1960 (Box 10)
    - Metro Sunday comics network contest, undated (Box 10)
    - News releases, 1958; 1962-1963 (Box 10)
    - New York World's Fair, 1964 (Box 11)
    - Notes by Greene, undated (Box 11)
    - Panel Discussion "Is this strip necessary?" promotional material, undated (Box 11)
    - Programs, undated (Box 11)
    - Public Relations reports, 1958-1962 (Box 11)
    - Publicity, 1959-1960 (Box 11)
    - Report of activities, 1955-1957 (Box 11)
    - Speech by White, David M. (co-editor), 1959 Jan (Box 11)
    - Survey of newspaper reading among children "How Kids Read Comics", 1960 (Box 11)
    - Survey of reader values in terms of the life cycle, 1958; titled A Fourth Dimension in Print Media Evaluation, removed and in Rare Books
- Published and printed material
  - About Greene
    - Newspaper clippings, 1933-1965; 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Publications by title C-Y, 1935; 1942,; 1946,; 1953,; 1956-1957,; 1960-1964; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Biographical Material, includes typed biographies, miscellaneous artwork, photographs of cartoonists
    - A-Z, 1950s; 4 folders (Box 14)
  - About and by others
    - About the cartoonists, 1938-1965; 2 folders (Box 11)
      Nurse Nellie's Waiting Room Reader, Cartoon Humor, Here's How America's Cartoonists Help to sell U.S. Savings Bonds, The Famous Artists Cartoon Course
    - Cartoonist's Guild of America, circa 1936-1939 (Box 11)
    - Hayes, Jeff, undated (Box 11)
    - Kingsman, Don, "All American", 1954 (Box 16)
    - King Features Syndicate, 1957; 1960-1961,; undated; promotional material for various comic strips, Sales Bulletin (Box 16)
    - Metropolitan Group Comics Calendar, 1949; 1951-1955; promotional material for various comic strips (Box 16)
    - Patterson, Russell "The Last Word in Humorous Illustration", undated (Box 16)
    - Red Ryder round up, 1961 (Box 16)
    - Report on European Political Cartooning by Jim Ivey, 1959; 1962 (Box 16)
    - Puck, the Comic Weekly, 1949; 1953-1954,; 1956-1958; advertising sales reports and assorted promotional material (Box 16)
    - The Walls Have Ears, 1942; promotional material (Box 16)
- Reference files
  - Accidents-Automobiles, 1926; 1931-1933,; 1936; 1946,; 1958,; 1961-1962,; 1964,; undated; writings, clippings, photographs, printed material, as well as some correspondence (Box 23)
    Accidents, Action, Advertising Club of Baltimore, Aeronautics (including U.S. Army and United Airlines), Aged, Aid Refugee Chinese intellectuals, Albany Institute of History and Art, Anatomy (male), Animals (domestic), Animals (wild), Army Gripes, Automobiles, Automobiles (Races)
  - Babies-Chalk Talks, 1928; 1931-1936,; 1940,; 1945,; 1949,; 1952,; 1962,; 1964; undated; writings, sketches, clippings, photographs, sketches, printed material, as well as some correspondence (Box 24)
    Babies, Birds, Birds Eye View, Boats, Buildings, Bunyan (drawings), Business Cartoon service catalog (1927), Carnivals, Cartoon capers, Cartoonists Guild of America (general correspondence 1954), Cartoonists Show for U.S. Savings Bonds (newspaper clippings 1949), Celebrities, Celebrities (outdated), Chalk Talks
  - Characters-Color, 1928-1935; 1946-1948,; 1957-1960,; undated; sketches, clippings, photographs, printed material, correspondence (Box 25)
    Characters, Children, Children's Home Society of New Jersey (correspondence and printed material 1957-1960), Chinese Students Club (photos 1948), Classical, Color (includes watercolor artwork)
  - Comic Art-Eisenhower, 1932-1936; 1938,; 1940-1941,; 1943-1949,; 1952-1953,; 1963,; undated; sketches, printed material, published material, clippings, photos, Association of American Editorial Cartoonists news (Box 26)
    Comic Art: An Occupation, Information and Career Guide, Comics Book Controversy (published material), Comics in the Classroom, Connolly, Joseph, Cops, Crowds, Current News Figures-Celebrities (photos), Dairy, Dance, Dressing, Drybrush, Eating, Editorial Cartoons (1963), Eisenhower (photos)
  - Expressions-Horses, 1930-1934; 1936-1937,; 1945-1946,; 1951,; 1955,; 1957,; 1959,; 1962-1963,; undated; notes, typed material, sketches, printed material, published material, clippings, photos, (Box 27)
    Expressions, Fishing (photos), Foreign Students, Girls (Glamour), Guns, Hands and Feet, A History of the Air Proving Ground- Eglin Air Force Base (proofs), History of Comics, Holidays (Armistice Day, Christmas, Easter, Female Figure, Fourth of July, Labor Day, Lincoln's birthday, Memorial Day, New Year's, Thanksgiving, Valentine's Day, Washington's birthday, Hollywood, Hornet's Nest (script)
  - Hospital-News, 1934; 1946,; 1955-1958,; 1960-1962,; undated; photos, clippings, published material, sketches, letter from the Red Cross, NCS, writings (Box 28)